VARSHINI TENETI

New York, NY | +1 (303) 847-8465 | tenetivarshini@gmail.com | LinkedIn

SUMMARY

Software Developer with over 3.5+ years of experience in Full-stack development and AWS certified developer. Accomplished in developing responsive web applications and optimizing system performance using technologies like React.js, Spring Boot, and modern JavaScript. Expertise in agile methodologies, project management, and improving customer satisfaction rates.

EDUCATION

University of Cincinnati

Cincinnati, OH

Master of Science in Information Technology (GPA:4.0/4.0)

Malla Reddy Engineering College for Women

Hyderabad, IN

Bachelor of Technology in Electronics and Communication Engineering (GPA:3.50/4.0)

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming Languages/Technologies: Java, J2EE, Python, Go, PHP, C, C#, C++, SQL, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, TypeScript, GraphQL, Kotlin.

Frameworks/Libraries: Angular, React.js, Vue.js, Node.js, .NET, ASP.NET, Django, Flask, Spring Boot, Spring MVC, Bootstrap, Express.js, REST API's.

Databases: SQL Server, MySQL, NoSQL, MongoDB, PostgreSQL, Oracle, DynamoDB, Relational Databases.

Tools: Visual studio, Android Studio, WordPress, Adobe, GitHub, Eclipse IDE, JIRA, CI/CD, Jenkins, Docker, Terraform, Kubernetes.

Cloud, OS & others: AWS, Azure, Git, GCP, MacOS, Linux, Windows, Kafka, Microservices, UI/UX, Data Structures.

Methodologies: Agile/Scrum, Software development life cycle, Object Oriented Analysis.

WORK EXPERIENCE

PTC Boston, MA

Full Stack Developer

Jan 2024 – Present

- Spearheaded the development and optimization of an enterprise-level Java application, enhancing system performance by 40% and reducing response times by 30% through efficient code refactoring and multi-threading techniques.
- Led the development of a comprehensive e-commerce web application using the MERN stack, increasing user engagement by 45% and reducing page load times by 35% through the optimization of React components and Node.js backend services.
- Designed and implemented RESTful web services using Spring Boot and Node.js, improving data exchange efficiency by 25% and contributing to a 20% increase in overall system interoperability and user satisfaction.

Cognizant Technology Solutions

Hyderabad, IN

Software Developer (Programmer Analyst)

Jul 2021 - Dec 2022

- Optimized a responsive internal dashboard using Next.js & TypeScript, improving load times and employee engagement by 40% and reducing type-related bugs by 30%.
- Architected and implemented the initial development of the internal recruitment platform using React.js and TypeScript, creating a responsive UI that improved user experience by 25% and navigation efficiency by 40% across various recruitment features.
- Developed a robust backend with Java and Spring Boot with efficient data management, API services, and secure authentication protocols (OAuth 2.0, JWT) enhancing data security and increase productivity by 20% across departments.
- Implemented responsive design and automated testing (Jest, JUnit), improving mobile usage by 40%, increasing user satisfaction by 30%, boosting code coverage to 90%, and optimizing database queries for 45% faster load times.
- Collaborated with UI/UX to implement an intuitive interface and designed RESTful APIs integrating 3+ internal systems, reducing navigation-related support tickets by 15% and improving cross-functional efficiency by 30% through streamlined data access.

EPAM Systems

Hyderabad, IN

Junior Software Developer

Mar 2020 - Jul 2021

- Built a responsive e-commerce web application focusing on optimal user experiences using front-end components like React.js and Nodes.js for server-side logic, resulting in a 40% increase in mobile user engagement.
- Integrated RESTful APIs using Express.js and refined state management with Redux, enhancing product search functionality and reducing average search time by 25%, resulting in increased user satisfaction.
- Attained a 30% boost in database performance by implementing enhanced MongoDB storage and retrieval strategies, resulting in faster query execution and enhanced system responsiveness.
- Implemented Jenkins-driven CI/CD pipelines, reducing deployment time by 50% and boosting software quality and team productivity by 30%. Collaborated in Agile environment to meet milestones and enhance coordination.

PROJECTS

Phishing Email Detection System | *MERN stack*, *ML* & *AWS*.

- Led a team in designing a web application using MERN Stack, ensuring seamless and efficient development process. Implemented feature extraction algorithms for phishing URL detection, achieving a 50% increase in early threat detection rates.
- Deployed the application on AWS for scalability, reliability and integrated with existing email systems, boosting overall cybersecurity defenses by 45% and reducing downtime by 30%.